<VariationArchive RecordType="classified" VariationID="8661" VariationName="NG_011688.2:g.(209254_?)_(210980_212428)del" VariationType="Deletion" Accession="VCV000008661" Version="6" NumberOfSubmissions="1" NumberOfSubmitters="1" DateLastUpdated="2023-11-11" DateCreated="2018-05-21" MostRecentSubmission="2023-11-11">
  <RecordStatus>current</RecordStatus>
  <Species>Homo sapiens</Species>
  <ClassifiedRecord>
    <SimpleAllele AlleleID="23700" VariationID="8661">
      <GeneList>
        <Gene Symbol="GHR" FullName="growth hormone receptor" GeneID="2690" HGNC_ID="HGNC:4263" Source="submitted" RelationshipType="asserted, but not computed">
          <Location>
            <CytogeneticLocation>5p13.1-12</CytogeneticLocation>
            <SequenceLocation Assembly="GRCh38" AssemblyAccessionVersion="GCF_000001405.38" AssemblyStatus="current" Chr="5" Accession="NC_000005.10" start="42423439" stop="42721878" display_start="42423439" display_stop="42721878" Strand="+" />
            <SequenceLocation Assembly="GRCh37" AssemblyAccessionVersion="GCF_000001405.25" AssemblyStatus="previous" Chr="5" Accession="NC_000005.9" start="42423876" stop="42721979" display_start="42423876" display_stop="42721979" Strand="+" />
          </Location>
          <OMIM>600946</OMIM>
        </Gene>
      </GeneList>
      <Name>NG_011688.2:g.(209254_?)_(210980_212428)del</Name>
      <VariantType>Deletion</VariantType>
      <Location>
        <CytogeneticLocation>5p13-p12</CytogeneticLocation>
      </Location>
      <OtherNameList>
        <Name>EX3DEL</Name>
      </OtherNameList>
      <HGVSlist>
        <HGVS Type="genomic">
          <NucleotideExpression sequenceAccessionVersion="NG_011688.2" sequenceAccession="NG_011688" sequenceVersion="2" change="g.(209254_?)_(210980_212428)del">
            <Expression>NG_011688.2:g.(209254_?)_(210980_212428)del</Expression>
          </NucleotideExpression>
        </HGVS>
      </HGVSlist>
      <XRefList>
        <XRef Type="Allelic variant" ID="600946.0031" DB="OMIM" />
      </XRefList>
      <Comment DataSource="NCBI curation" Type="public">NCBI staff provided an HGVS expression for allelic variant 600946.0031 from the restriction map and primers used to detect the deletion.</Comment>
    </SimpleAllele>
    <RCVList>
      <RCVAccession Title="NG_011688.2:g.(209254_?)_(210980_212428)del AND Increased responsiveness to growth hormone" Accession="RCV000009193" Version="9">
        <ClassifiedConditionList TraitSetID="2376">
          <ClassifiedCondition DB="MedGen" ID="C3888131">Increased responsiveness to growth hormone</ClassifiedCondition>
        </ClassifiedConditionList>
        <RCVClassifications>
          <GermlineClassification>
            <ReviewStatus>no assertion criteria provided</ReviewStatus>
            <Description DateLastEvaluated="2008-07-01" SubmissionCount="1">Pathogenic</Description>
          </GermlineClassification>
        </RCVClassifications>
      </RCVAccession>
    </RCVList>
    <Classifications>
      <GermlineClassification DateLastEvaluated="2008-07-01" NumberOfSubmissions="1" NumberOfSubmitters="1" DateCreated="2018-05-21" MostRecentSubmission="2023-11-11">
        <ReviewStatus>no assertion criteria provided</ReviewStatus>
        <Description>Pathogenic</Description>
        <Citation Type="general">
          <ID Source="PubMed">10764769</ID>
        </Citation>
        <Citation Type="general">
          <ID Source="PubMed">11836270</ID>
        </Citation>
        <Citation Type="general">
          <ID Source="PubMed">15208626</ID>
        </Citation>
        <Citation Type="general">
          <ID Source="PubMed">16291706</ID>
        </Citation>
        <Citation Type="general">
          <ID Source="PubMed">16804042</ID>
        </Citation>
        <Citation Type="general">
          <ID Source="PubMed">17090634</ID>
        </Citation>
        <Citation Type="general">
          <ID Source="PubMed">17426087</ID>
        </Citation>
        <Citation Type="general">
          <ID Source="PubMed">17711923</ID>
        </Citation>
        <Citation Type="general">
          <ID Source="PubMed">17925340</ID>
        </Citation>
        <Citation Type="general">
          <ID Source="PubMed">18029459</ID>
        </Citation>
        <Citation Type="general">
          <ID Source="PubMed">18397980</ID>
        </Citation>
        <Citation Type="general">
          <ID Source="PubMed">18445665</ID>
        </Citation>
        <ConditionList>
          <TraitSet ID="2376" Type="Disease" ContributesToAggregateClassification="true">
            <Trait ID="10465" Type="Disease">
              <Name>
                <ElementValue Type="Preferred">Increased responsiveness to growth hormone</ElementValue>
              </Name>
              <XRef ID="C3888131" DB="MedGen" />
            </Trait>
          </TraitSet>
        </ConditionList>
      </GermlineClassification>
    </Classifications>
    <ClinicalAssertionList>
      <ClinicalAssertion ID="29410" SubmissionDate="2021-02-16" DateLastUpdated="2023-11-11" DateCreated="2013-04-04">
        <ClinVarSubmissionID localKey="600946.0031_INCREASED RESPONSIVENESS TO GROWTH HORMONE" title="GHR, EX3DEL_INCREASED RESPONSIVENESS TO GROWTH HORMONE" />
        <ClinVarAccession Accession="SCV000029410" DateUpdated="2023-11-11" DateCreated="2013-04-04" Type="SCV" Version="7" SubmitterName="OMIM" OrgID="3" OrganizationCategory="resource" />
        <RecordStatus>current</RecordStatus>
        <Classification DateLastEvaluated="2008-07-01">
          <ReviewStatus>no assertion criteria provided</ReviewStatus>
          <GermlineClassification>Pathogenic</GermlineClassification>
        </Classification>
        <Assertion>variation to disease</Assertion>
        <ObservedInList>
          <ObservedIn>
            <Sample>
              <Origin>germline</Origin>
              <Species>human</Species>
              <AffectedStatus>not provided</AffectedStatus>
            </Sample>
            <Method>
              <MethodType>literature only</MethodType>
            </Method>
            <ObservedData>
              <Attribute Type="Description">In humans, GHR transcripts are present in 2 isoforms that differ by the retention or exclusion of exon 3. Pantel et al. (2000) demonstrated that the GHR isoform that lacks exon 3 (d3GHR) is transcribed from a gene that carries a 2.7-kb deletion spanning exon 3 and its flanking sequences. This deletion results in the loss of amino acid residues 7 through 28 and an ala6-to-asp (A6D) substitution in the terminal part of the extracellular receptor domain. The d3GHR allele results in increased sensitivity to therapeutically administered GH (see 604271).</Attribute>
              <Citation>
                <ID Source="PubMed">10764769</ID>
              </Citation>
              <XRef DB="OMIM" ID="604271" Type="MIM" />
            </ObservedData>
            <ObservedData>
              <Attribute Type="Description">Growth hormone is used to increase height in short children who are not deficient in growth hormone, but its efficacy varies widely across individuals. Dos Santos et al. (2004) found that the isoform of the GHR gene that lacks exon 3 (d3GHR) was associated with 1.7 to 2 times more growth acceleration induced by growth hormone than the full-length isoform (p less than 0.0001). In transfection experiments, the transduction of growth hormone signaling through d3GHR homo- or heterodimers was approximately 30% higher than through full-length GHR homodimers (p less than 0.0001). Dos Santos et al. (2004) stated that one-half of Europeans are heterozygous or homozygous with respect to the allele encoding the d3GHR isoform, which is dominant over the full-length isoform. Thus, the polymorphism in exon 3 of GHR is important in growth hormone pharmacogenetics. Transfective dose-response studies in all categories of children treated with growth hormone would determine the optimal growth hormone dosage for their GHR genotype. This may contribute to a switch from fixed dosage therapy to a more personalized adjustment of dose.</Attribute>
              <Citation>
                <ID Source="PubMed">15208626</ID>
              </Citation>
            </ObservedData>
            <ObservedData>
              <Attribute Type="Description">In short non-GH-deficient short-for-gestational-age (SGA) children, Carrascosa et al. (2006) found that both spontaneous growth rate and responsiveness to 66 microg/kg per day of GH therapy were similar for each d3/fl-GHR genotype carried. Carrascosa et al. (2008) hypothesized that higher doses of GH would mask the lower dose differences seen in the response of those with d3/fl-GHR genotypes. They evaluated, in short SGA patients, 2-year growth response to GH therapy (32.1 +/- 3.8 microg/kg per day) according to d3/fl-GHR genotype. They found that in short SGA children, 2-year growth response to GH therapy at this dosage was similar for each d3/fl-GHR genotype carried, as occurred in their previous study (Carrascosa et al., 2006). In a study of 219 short SGA children, of which 60 had entered puberty, Audi et al. (2008) found that d3/fl-GHR genotypes did not seem to influence prepubertal or pubertal insulin sensitivity indexes or their changes over 2 years of GH therapy.</Attribute>
              <Citation>
                <ID Source="PubMed">16804042</ID>
              </Citation>
              <Citation>
                <ID Source="PubMed">17925340</ID>
              </Citation>
              <Citation>
                <ID Source="PubMed">18445665</ID>
              </Citation>
            </ObservedData>
            <ObservedData>
              <Attribute Type="Description">Binder et al. (2006) tested the association of the d3GHR polymorphism in 2 distinct groups of rhGH-treated patients, short girls with Turner syndrome and short children born SGA. No significant difference in height, spontaneous height velocity, IGF1, and IGFBP3 levels was found at the start of the rhGH therapy in the 3 GHR genotype groups studied. At the first year of treatment, girls with Turner syndrome carrying 1 or 2 d3GHR alleles showed a significantly higher increment in height velocity (P = 0.019) and exceeded their growth prediction significantly (P = 0.007), whereas their increments of IGF1 and IGFBP3, weight, and height were not significantly different. Carriers of d3GHR in the group of short children born SGA grew significantly faster than predicted (P = 0.023). However, in comparison to the carriers of full-length GHR, gain of height velocity was not significantly higher (P = 0.067). The mean gain of height associated with d3GHR accounted for approximately 0.75 cm in SGA and 1.5 cm in Turner syndrome during the first year of rhGH therapy. Their data supported the theory that there is increased responsiveness to high-dose rhGH in association with the d3GHR genotype. The magnitude of this effect may depend on the primary origin of the short stature.</Attribute>
              <Citation>
                <ID Source="PubMed">16291706</ID>
              </Citation>
            </ObservedData>
            <ObservedData>
              <Attribute Type="Description">Jorge et al. (2006) performed a genotype and retrospective analysis on data of 75 patients with severe GHD. They found that patients who had at least 1 d3GHR allele had a small but statistically significant higher first-year growth response and taller final height after hGH treatment than patients who were homozygous for the GHRfl allele, treated under the same conditions.</Attribute>
              <Citation>
                <ID Source="PubMed">11836270</ID>
              </Citation>
            </ObservedData>
            <ObservedData>
              <Attribute Type="Description">In a study of 368 healthy adult women, Kenth et al. (2007) found no correlation between the GHR exon 3 genotype and final adult height and bone mineral density.</Attribute>
              <Citation>
                <ID Source="PubMed">17090634</ID>
              </Citation>
            </ObservedData>
            <ObservedData>
              <Attribute Type="Description">In a study of 115 healthy adolescents who were divided into those born SGA and appropriate for gestational age with or without intrauterine growth restriction, Jensen et al. (2007) found that the d3GHR allele was associated with increased spontaneous postnatal growth velocity, but with decreased fetal growth velocity in the SGA group.</Attribute>
              <Citation>
                <ID Source="PubMed">17426087</ID>
              </Citation>
            </ObservedData>
            <ObservedData>
              <Attribute Type="Description">Schreiner et al. (2007) studied association of the GHRd3 isoform with postnatal catch-up growth in very low birth weight preterm infants. Children homozygous or heterozygous for the GHRd3 allele showed a significantly higher rate of postnatal catch-up, compared with those homozygous for GHRfl allele. They concluded that their results define the GHR exon 3 genotype as a predictor for the postnatal growth pattern of very low birth weight preterm infants. Those who carry at least one GHRd3 allele are more likely to catch up.</Attribute>
              <Citation>
                <ID Source="PubMed">17711923</ID>
              </Citation>
            </ObservedData>
            <ObservedData>
              <Attribute Type="Description">In 181 subjects with severe isolated GH deficiency treated with recombinant human GH, Raz et al. (2008) studied the impact of exon 3 GHR genotype in terms of the initial height velocity (HV) resulting from treatment and upon adult height. After the first 2 years on recombinant human GH treatment, HV SD score (SDS) as well as height gain were greater in subjects with the GHR d3/d3 genotype when compared with the subjects presenting with the GHR fl/fl genotype. A GHR d3 allele dose-dependent effect was found for both HV SDS and height gain. However, there was no significant difference in final adult height and height SDS according to the exon 3 genotypes.</Attribute>
              <Citation>
                <ID Source="PubMed">18029459</ID>
              </Citation>
            </ObservedData>
            <ObservedData>
              <Attribute Type="Description">In a study of 99 adult GH-deficient patients receiving recombinant human GH (rhGH) replacement therapy, Van der Klaauw et al. (2008) found that the d3GHR genotype was associated with differences in efficacy of short-term (1 year), but not long-term (5 years), rhGH replacement with respect to IGF1 and lipid metabolism.</Attribute>
              <Citation>
                <ID Source="PubMed">18397980</ID>
              </Citation>
            </ObservedData>
          </ObservedIn>
        </ObservedInList>
        <SimpleAllele>
          <GeneList>
            <Gene Symbol="GHR" />
          </GeneList>
          <Name>GHR, EX3DEL</Name>
          <VariantType>Variation</VariantType>
          <OtherNameList>
            <Name Type="NonHGVS">EX3DEL</Name>
          </OtherNameList>
          <XRefList>
            <XRef DB="OMIM" ID="600946.0031" Type="Allelic variant" />
          </XRefList>
        </SimpleAllele>
        <TraitSet Type="Disease">
          <Trait Type="Disease">
            <Name>
              <ElementValue Type="Preferred">INCREASED RESPONSIVENESS TO GROWTH HORMONE</ElementValue>
            </Name>
          </Trait>
        </TraitSet>
      </ClinicalAssertion>
    </ClinicalAssertionList>
    <TraitMappingList>
      <TraitMapping ClinicalAssertionID="29410" TraitType="Disease" MappingType="Name" MappingValue="INCREASED RESPONSIVENESS TO GROWTH HORMONE" MappingRef="Preferred">
        <MedGen CUI="C3888131" Name="Increased responsiveness to growth hormone" />
      </TraitMapping>
    </TraitMappingList>
  </ClassifiedRecord>
</VariationArchive>

